Finding Aid for Research Seminar in Quantitative Economics (University of Michigan) records, 1960-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Research Seminar in Quantitative Economics (University of Michigan) records 1960-2015 1975-1989
Research Seminar in Quantitative Economics.
7 linear feet
2014086 Bimu 2
The Research Seminar in Quantitative Economics is an economic modeling and forecasting unit at the University of Michigan. The collection ranges from 1960 to 2014 with the bulk of the material being from 1975-1989 and is primarily made up of the results of the seminar's economic forecasting and papers that were written for the seminar.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated by the U-M Research Seminar in Quantitative Economics (Donor No. 10628 ) beginning in September 2011.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open without restriction.
The Research Seminar in Quantitative Economics (RSQE) is an economic modeling and forecasting unit which has been in operation at the University of Michigan since 1952. Four times a year, RSQE provides forecasts of both the United States national economy and the Michigan economy. The University of Michigan's Annual Economic Outlook Conference, the longest-running such event in the United States, is put on by RSQE and is held in Ann Arbor each November. The attendees at the Conference are primarily upper level business and government economists and analysts from all over the country (with the Midwest over-represented) and from all types of industry, plus local academics from the University of Michigan and the nearby region.
The Research Seminar in Quantitative Economics (RSQE) collection is primarily made up of the results of the seminar's economic forecasting and papers that were written for the seminar. The collection is made of four series: Forecasts, Presentation Papers, Time Series Papers, and Economic Outlook.
Subjects:
Conference on the Economic Outlook.; Economic forecasting--Michigan.; Economic forecasting--United States.; Michigan--Economic conditions.; Research Seminar in Quantitative Economics.; United States--Economic conditions.; University of Michigan. Department of Economics.
Contributors:
Fulton, George A., 1948-; Hymans, Saul H.
- Forecasts
  The Forecasts series (4 linear feet) contains yearly economic forecasts determined by the RSQE for the United States and Michigan. Each year contains the material that was publicly released regarding the economic predictions, as well as changes to the predictions as they became available in subsequent months.
  - 1960 (Box 1)
  - 1962 (Box 1)
  - 1964 (Box 1)
  - 1966-1985 (Box 1)
  - 1986-1993 (Box 2)
  - 1994-2001 (Box 3)
  - 2002-2010 (Box 4)
  - 2012-2015 (Box 4)
  - 2015-2016 (Box 4)
- Presentation Papers
  The Presentation Papers series (1.5 linear feet) contains papers and research proposals that were to be presented at the Research Seminar or worked on by members of the Seminar. Some papers also contain notes on the research, though most are only the final product. Papers are organized alphabetically, but the author(s) and date are included in the finding aid if they were on the material.
  - The Allocation of Household Income to Food Consumption by Hymans and Shapiro, 1975 (Box 5)
  - An Open Economy Analysis of the dynamic Properties of the Michigan Quarterly Econometric Model by Howrey and Hymans, 1992 (Box 5)
  - The Asia Foundation Pacific Economic Outlook Project by Hymans and Krause, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Asymptotic Distribution in Regression Models with Stochastic Explanatory Variables by Howrey and Hymans, 1985 (Box 5)
  - A Central Limit Theorem with Applications to Econometrics by Howrey and Hymans, 1981, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Divergence, Convergence, and the Gains from Trade by Hymans and Stafford, 1993 (Box 5)
  - The Dynamics of the Michigan Quarterly Econometric Model of the U.S. Economy 1981 (Box 5)
  - An Econometric Model Forecast of 1975 by Hymans and Shapiro, 1975 (Box 5)
  - Econometric Review of Alternative Fiscal and Monetary Policies 1966-1975 II by Hymans and Shapiro (Box 5)
  - Econometric Review of Alternative Fiscal and Monetary Policies 1971-1975 by Hirsch, Hymans, and Shapiro, 1977, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Econometric Review of Alternative Fiscal and Monetary Policies 1971-1975 by Hirsch, Hymans, and Shapiro, 1978, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Estimation of the Covariance Matrix of the Least Squares Regression Coefficients by Keener, Kmenta, and Weber, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Fiscal Policy and Aggregate Demand by Aschauer, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Inflation in the United States 1953-1974 An Overview and Preliminary Analysis by Shapiro, 1974 (Box 5)
  - Kemp-Roth Proposal, 1978 (Box 5)
  - A Lack-of-fit Test for Econometric Applications to Cross-section Data by Doran and Kmenta, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Macroeconomic Effects of Fiscal Policy by Aschauer and Greenwood, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Macro-econometric Model Building in Socialist and Non-Socialist Countries by Shapiro and Halabuk, 1975 (Box 5)
  - Macro-econometric Models of the Soviet Union and Eastern European Economics by Shapiro (Box 5)
  - The Measurement and Determination of Loanable Funds Saving by Howrey and Hymans, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Median Voter Models and the Growth of Government Services by Hymans, 1981 (Box 5)
  - The Michigan Quarterly Econometric Model of the U.S. Economy by Hymans, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Missing Measurements in a Regression Problem with No Auxiliary Relations by Balestra and Kmenta (Box 5)
  - Money Demand and the Efficacy of Fiscal Policy, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Money Demand Equation (Box 5)
  - Multiple Minima in the Estimation of Models with Autoregressive Disturbances by Doran and Kmenta (Box 5)
  - NBER Tape Programs (Box 5)
  - New Methods for Using Monthly Data to Improve Forecast Accuracy by Howrey, 1989 (Box 5)
  - On the Analysis and Improvement of Macroeconometric Forecast Accuracy by Howrey, Hymans, and Donihue, 1987 (Box 5)
  - On the Problem of Missing Measurements in the Estimation of Economic Relationships by Kmenta, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Optimal Control and Macroeconometric Models by Shapiro, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Optimal Critical Regions for Pre-Test Estimators Using a Bayes Risk Criterion by Roehrig, 1983 (Box 5)
  - The Outlook for the U.S. Economy 1988-1990 by Hymans and Krause, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Policy Simulations for St. Louis Meeting by Howrey, Hymans, and Shapiro, 1975 (Box 5)
  - Proposal to House Fiscal Legacy, 1977-1981 (folder 1 of 2) (Box 5)
  - Proposal to House Fiscal Legacy, 1977-1981 (folder 2 of 2) (Box 6)
  - Proposed Financial Sector for the Michigan Quarterly Econometric Model of the U.S. Economy by Holbrook (Box 6)
  - Relative Concentration of Employment in Manufacturing, Michigan and the U.S. by Barkey, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Research on Reliability of Economic Models -- Proposal, 1977-1981, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Some New Results on Ridge Regression Estimation by Lin and Kmenta (Box 6)
  - Tools for Forecasting and Structural Analysis of Economic Regions by Fulton, 1987 (Box 6)
  - A "True" Time Series and Its Indicators: An Alternative Approach by Edwards and Howrey (Box 6)
  - The U.S. Economic Outlook for 1975-1976 by Shapiro, 1975 (Box 6)
  - The Use of Outside Information in Econometric Forecasting by Howrey, Hymans, and Greene, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Users Guide for the Michigan Quarterly Econometric Model (Box 6)
  - Validation and Improvement of Macroeconometric Models by Howrey and Hymans, 1975 (Box 6)
  - What is an Econometric Model Anyway? by Hymans, 1979 (Box 6)
- Time Series Papers
  The Time Series Papers series (.5 linear feet) are papers dealing with the topic of time-series economics. Based on the papers included, it is possible that these papers were set to be combined into a book on time-series economics. As such, some papers from the Presentation Papers series may overlap with the papers included in this series.
  - Aggregate Inventory Investment: An Exploratory Analysis by Howrey and Lown (Box 6)
  - An Analysis of RSQE Forecasts: 1971-1992 by Howrey, 1995 (Box 6)
  - Appendix to Accompany: Estimating the Distributional Impact of Time-of-day Pricing of Electricity by Howrey and Varian, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Asymptotic Theory by Howrey, 1983 (Box 6)
  - Check the Record! An Evaluation of RSQE Forecasts: 1971-1987 by Howrey (Box 6)
  - A Continuous, Piecewise Linear Energy-Temperature Regression Model by Howrey, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Data Dependent Systems and Exponential Smoothing by Pandit (Box 6)
  - Data Revision, Reconstruction, and Prediction: An Application to Inventory Investment by Howrey, 1983 (Box 6)
  - ECON: MSA-A Program for Multivariate Spectrum Analysis by Howrey, 1983 (Box 6)
  - Econometric Forecast of Electricity Demand in the South Atlantic Region by Chern, Lin, and Holcomb (Box 6)
  - Econometric Review of Alternative Fiscal and Monetary Policies 1971-1975 by Hirsch, Hymans, and Shapiro, 1978 (Box 6)
  - Estimating the Distributional Impact of Time-of-day Pricing of Electricity by Howrey and Varian, 1984 (Box 6)
  - Exchange Rate Forecasts with the Michigan Quarterly Econometric Model of the U.S. Economy by Howrey, 1993 (Box 6)
  - Forecasting with State-Dependent Autoregressive Models by Howrey and Lettvin (Box 6)
  - A History of Macroeconometric Model-Building by Bodkin, Klein, and Marwah, 1991 (Box 6)
  - The Identification Problem by Howrey (Box 6)
  - Index for Reprints 1994 (Box 6)
  - Introduction to Statistical Time Series: Chapter 1 (Box 6)
  - An Introduction to the Theory and Practice of Econometrics by Howrey, 1981 (Box 6)
  - Macroeconometrics Amidst Sense and Nonsense by Hymans, 1983 (Box 6)
  - Managerialism and Market Imperfections by Holl (Box 6)
  - Mean Squared Error comparisons and Econometric Model Evaluation by Howrey, 1978 (Box 6)
  - The Measurement and Determination of Loanable-Funds Saving by Howrey and Hymans (Box 6)
  - Merging Monthly and Quarterly Forecasts: Experience with MQEM by Howrey, Hymans, and Donihue (Box 6)
  - The Money Sector of the Michigan Quarterly Econometric Model (Box 6)
  - A Multivariate Time Series Approach to Modeling Macroeconomic Sequences, 1977 (Box 6)
  - Nonlinear Regression by Howrey, 1986 (Box 6)
  - On the Accuracy of Econometric Forecasting Models by Howrey and Hymans, 1986 (Box 6)
  - An Open Economy Analysis of the Dynamic Properties of the Michigan Quarterly Econometric Model of the U.S. Economy by Howrey and Hymans (Box 6)
  - Perspectives on the Accuracy of Macro-econometric Forecasting Models by Shapiro and Garman, 1978 (Box 6)
  - The Policy Implications of "Crowding Out" by Holbrook and Howrey, 1976 (Box 6)
  - The Practice of Macroeconometric Model Building and its Rationale by Howrey, Klein, McCarthy, and Schink (Box 6)
  - Prediction, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Procedural Effects of Pricing Electricity by Time Use (Box 6)
  - Properties of Maximum Likelihood Estimators by Howrey, 1984 (Box 6)
  - Residual Spectrum Analysis with Applications to Consumption Function Estimation by Howrey (Box 6)
  - The Role of Time Series Analysis in Econometric Model Evaluation (Box 6)
  - Saving, Investment, and Social Security, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Seminar-Chicago by Howrey 1979 (Box 6)
  - Specification, Estimation, and Analysis of Macroeconometric Models by Fair (Box 6)
  - Stabilization Policy with Stochastic and Nonlinear Elements by Sengupta (Box 6)
  - Symmetric, Definite, and Idempotent Matrices by Howrey, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Time Series Book: Chapter 1 (Box 6)
  - Time Series Book: Chapter 2 (Box 6)
  - Time Series Book: Chapter 3 (Box 6)
  - Time Series Forecasts with Observation Error by Howrey, 1977 (Box 6)
  - A "True" Time Series and its Indicators: An Alternative Approach by Edward and Howrey, 1990-1991 (Box 6)
  - The Use of Monthly Data to Update Quarterly Forecasts by Howrey and Donihue, 1984 (Box 6)
  - The Use of Preliminary Data in Econometric Forecasting by Howrey, 1978 (Box 6)
- Economic Outlook
  The Economic Outlook series (1 linear foot) contains published books from the annual Conference on the Economic Outlook, put on by the RSQE and held at the University of Michigan while being sponsored by the Department of Economics. Books contain the economic predictions for the following year as well as the papers presented at the conference. The series is missing books for 1955-1963 and 2012.
  - 1953-1954 (Box 7)
  - 1964-2011 (Box 7)
  - 2013 (Box 7)